<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Eureka College at 160</title>
    <description>This Week in Eureka College History commemorates the 160th anniversary of the founding of Eureka College on February 6, 1855, and is scheduled to run weekly through February 6, 2016.</description>
    <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 12:37:38 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 12:37:38 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>September 10</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It all began on Sept. 10, 1848. That’s when Walnut Grove Seminary, the forerunner of Eureka College, opened its doors as an educational institution. Classes were offered to young men and young women in a one-room schoolhouse located near the first Christian Church built in the community of Walnut Grove (located where Olio Township Cemetery is now situated). Asa Starbuck Fisher was the first professor to teach at the institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/seminary.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The Seminary&quot; alt=&quot;The Seminary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Seminary&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rough-hewn school building was a single-room structure that measured 16 by 16 feet. The building had been constructed a few years earlier by Jonathan Tressler, a local carpenter, and the structure was moved from the present southwestern corner of the cemetery lands to the northern site. In 1849, an additional room that measured 16 by 24 feet was added to the original structure. Three of the founders of the Walnut Grove Seminary – Ben Major, David Deweese and Elias Myers – each pledged $150 to finance the relocation of the structure and the improvements and additions that were made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stone now marks the spot where the Walnut Grove Seminary stood. This marker was dedicated by the Woodford County Historical Society on June 14, 1926. The inscription on the stone reads:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;HERE BEGAN

THE FIRST SCHOOL

IN EUREKA

1848&lt;br /&gt;

THE BEGINNING

OF EUREKA COLLEGE&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the mid-1850s the seminary building was no longer being used because the Academy Building had become the center of activity, and the structure was sold to a local family by the name of King. The King family would take in female boarders who attended Walnut Grove Academy. Several decades later, only two elderly daughters of the King family remained in the home, and the old seminary building was nicknamed the &amp;ldquo;Queen&amp;rsquo;s Palace&amp;rdquo; by local residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was from these humble origins that Eureka College came into being. It was through the foresight of these founders that an institution of higher education was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Sept. 11, 1954, more than 100 volunteers arrived on the Eureka College campus to spend an entire Saturday painting Lida&amp;rsquo;s Wood Residence Hall. This task was especially important then as the college prepared for the huge centennial celebration that would take place during the spring semester of the 1954-55 school year. Many of the commemorative events associated with the centennial, like dinners, teas, etc., were to be held in Lida&amp;rsquo;s Wood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This massive work day came only a few months after Ira Langston had assumed the presidency of Eureka College. One of the stipulations that Langston had raised before accepting the position was that he wanted to make sure that Eureka College had the support of the many Christian Churches in Illinois. The volunteers who turned out on Sept.11 included representatives of 26 Illinois congregations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/september-10</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/september-10</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>September 3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-jRinker-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Jacob Rinker&quot; alt=&quot;Jacob Rinker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Jacob Rinker&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 6, 1887, Jacob A. Rinker was born. From Table Grove, Ricker graduated from Eureka College in 1918. He taught at the college from 1919 until his retirement in 1957. Few individuals have had as lasting an impact upon the campus as Rinker did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after he began teaching at the college, Rinker began construction of a rustic pioneer bungalow just south of Vennum Science Hall. He built this home in the early 1920s using local timber and stone and did all of the construction on his own. Rinker obtained the huge logs that were needed from the Mackinaw River bottomland six miles east of Eureka, and these were dragged to town by mule for use in constructing the home. Today Eureka College owns the property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/RinkerHouse_1930s.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Rinker House&quot; alt=&quot;Rinker House&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Rinker House c. 1930&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rinker also envisioned the site of what is today called the Rinker Amphitheater and began work on the terracing of the landscape in 1926. During the next few years, graduating classes donated funds to purchase the trees and shrubs that surround the theater. Rows of Lombardy poplars, Japanese barberry, and Tartarian honeysuckle were planted to surround the eight terraces designed to seat 5,000. Rinker developed the amphitheater for &lt;sup&gt;$&lt;/sup&gt;650. The site is used for Opening Convocation as well as for the presentation of plays and pageants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jacob Rinker died in 1974. In 1977, Eureka College dedicated the Rinker Conference Room in Vennum Science Hall in memory of his many contributions to the life of the college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-sBinkley-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Stephen Binkley&quot; alt=&quot;Stephen Binkley&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Stephen Binkley&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 1, 1987, Emeritus Professor of Chemistry Stephen B. Binkley died. He was a summa cum laude graduate of Eureka College, Class of &amp;lsquo;34. He earned a master&amp;rsquo;s degree and doctorate, both from the University of Nebraska. He married fellow EC alumnus Lois Grosse, Class of &#39;34, in 1934. Binkley was a noted chemist who spent his career engaged in both research and teaching through his work both in private industry and in higher education. He was a research chemist for Parke Davis &amp;amp; Co. and later the director of chemical research for Bristol Laboratories. He taught at the St. Louis University College of Medicine and at the University of Illinois College of Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a research chemist, Binkley was part of the team that discovered Vitamin K and Folic acid. Edward A. Doisy, who headed the research team, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1943 for his work in the discovery of Vitamin K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Binkley served Eureka College as a trustee for several terms, included as chairman from 1964&amp;ndash;69. He joined the EC faculty in 1972 and taught until 1986.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/september-3</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/september-3</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>August 27</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On Aug. 30, 1819, William Davenport and Eliza Major were married in Christian County, Ken. The marriage joined two families&amp;mdash;the Davenports and the Majors&amp;mdash;who would later play a significant role in the settlement of Walnut Grove (later Eureka) in what eventually became Woodford County, Ill. The familiar names Davenport and Major adorn school buildings, college residence halls and street signs in this community, making them an ever-present force in this town. A walk through Eureka&amp;rsquo;s Olio Cemetery reveals how significant these two families were in the formation of this community, as these early settlers and many of their progeny are buried there. Descendants of these families still live in Eureka and surrounding communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was common in early America for pioneer migrations to include several families that were united by marriage or by family relationships. Also, individuals who were co-religionists, in this case the Christian Church movement, often migrated together, and, in the process, founded new congregations in the communities they established. Often, pioneer communities experienced a type of serial migration where residents from one community moved to a new location and then convinced friends and relatives from back home to make a similar trek. The large concentration of early pioneers from Christian County, Ken., to this region suggests this type of migration pattern occurred as Walnut Grove was settled by pioneer families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although some pioneer families did inhabit this region in the early 1820s, it was in the mid-1830s that the Davenport and Major families relocated to central Illinois. A significant corps of the founding families associated with the history of Eureka College came to this region during Andrew Jackson&amp;rsquo;s second term as President of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-eStewart-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Ella Seass Stewart&quot; alt=&quot;Ella Seass Stewart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ella Seass Stewart&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of marriages, one took place on Aug. 20, 1890, when Elvira &amp;ldquo;Ella&amp;rdquo; Seass married her college beau, Oliver Wayne Stewart, both from the Class of 1890. The Stewarts wasted no time after leaving Eureka College to become involved in reform movements at the state and national levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ella Seass Stewart would eventually serve several terms as a national officer in the National American Woman Suffrage Association. She was among the women who were instrumental in having Illinois adopt woman suffrage legislation before it became national policy. Oliver Wayne Stewart was among the national leaders in the temperance movement and campaigned nationwide for the adoption of Prohibition. From 1899 to 1919 Stewart was the chairman of the National Prohibition Committee. When the nation was considering adoption of the Eighteenth Amendment providing for Prohibition, Stewart organized &amp;ldquo;The Flying Squadron&amp;rdquo; – a group of temperance advocates who traveled around the country speaking in support of the Prohibition measure from 1915 to 1920.
The college recently erected banners honoring 20 alumni for their outstanding achievements. Ella Seass Stewart’s image graces one of those banners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/banner-eStewart-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Ella Seass Stewart&quot; alt=&quot;Ella Seass Stewart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Ella Seass Stewart&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/august-27</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/august-27</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>August 20</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On Aug. 16, 2000, the demolition of Lida&amp;rsquo;s Wood residence hall began. The demolition of the structure and the removal of debris would be completed over the following 10 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lida&amp;rsquo;s Wood that was removed was not the original structure to bear that name. The original home of local attorney Robert T. Cassell was constructed in 1869. The Metamora lawyer had moved to Eureka and constructed a home here while his daughter attended Eureka College. The home was sold in the early 1880s to Wallace J. and Mary Ford who had moved to Illinois shortly after the death of President James Garfield. Ford had been the private secretary to Garfield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/lidas-wood.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Lida&#39;s Wood c. 1889&quot; alt=&quot;Lida&#39;s Wood c. 1889&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Lida&#39;s Wood c. 1889&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lida Ford, the young daughter of the Ford family, died at the residence on April 21, 1887. Shortly after her death, the Ford family decided to deed the home to Eureka College provided that it become a residence hall for women. The college agreed to do so and also agreed to two other stipulations in the original deed. The name of the residence hall had to memorialize Lida and the college had to add an annex onto the existing home to accommodate its use as a residence hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That original Lida&amp;rsquo;s Wood burned on Jan. 11, 1894.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The building was quickly reconstructed and was back in use as a completely new structure by 1895. For many of the next 105 years, Lida&amp;rsquo;s Wood would be the social center of the campus. The campus dining hall was located there prior to the construction of Dickinson Commons in 1962, and Ronald Reagan, Class of 1932, washed dishes in the kitchen when he was a student at Eureka College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/lidas-wood-1950s-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Lida&#39;s Wood c. 1950&quot; alt=&quot;Lida&#39;s Wood c. 1950&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Lida&#39;s Wood c. 1950&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Throughout its history, some maintained that the building was haunted by the benevolent ghost of Lida who did everything that she could to prevent another fire from destroying her home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1990s, as it celebrated its centennial, Lida&amp;rsquo;s Wood was truly showing its age. Deterioration of the architectural infrastructure had become a significant problem. The foundation of red brick upon which the hastily constructed 1895 structure had been built was beginning to crumble. As such, structural problems were many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The building was closed to student use during the 1999-2000 school year as a feasibility study was completed to determine whether the building could and should be renovated or whether the removal of the structure was necessary. When architectural reports indicated that the cost of renovations would be greater than half the cost of constructing a new building, the Board of Trustees decided in May 2000 to remove the structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-rHumbert-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Royal Humbert&quot; alt=&quot;Royal Humbert&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Royal Humbert&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Aug. 19, 1989, emeritus professor of religion and philosophy Royal Humbert died at age 79. Named after the legendary Christian missionary Royal Dye, it seem almost natural that Royal Humbert would eventually become a noted theologian and professor of religion and philosophy at Eureka College. He joined the faculty in 1948 and taught until his retirement in the mid-1970s. His wife, Lois, joined the faculty in 1954 as professor of piano and organ and director of the handbell choir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Humbert was known for being a rigorous teacher and a productive scholar. During his tenure at Eureka College he produced A Compend of Alexander Campbell&amp;rsquo;s Theology, with Commentary in the Form of Critical and Historical Footnotes. Edited by Royal Humbert. (St. Louis: Bethany Press, 1961).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon his retirement, the college established the Humbert Lecture Series to honor him. This endowed lecture series examines issues of theological or philosophical importance in the context of contemporary public life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/august-20</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/august-20</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>August 6</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On Aug. 6 1879, the Eureka College Board of Trustees announced a new marketing strategy aimed at attaining the goal of increasing enrollment at the college. The board announced that for the 1879&amp;ndash;1880 school year, students could attend Eureka College and live rent-free in the newly constructed campus boarding hall, Gentleman&amp;rsquo;s Hall No. 2. This invitation was extended to men and women, but they did not share the same boarding facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/gentlemans-hall-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Gentleman&#39;s Hall No. 2&quot; alt=&quot;Gentleman&#39;s Hall No. 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Gentleman&#39;s Hall No. 2&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This new facility, which was constructed directly east of the old Walnut Grove Academy building (located to the rear of the current Rinker Amphitheater) was built with the hope that &amp;ldquo;if you build it they will come.&amp;rdquo; The state-of-the-art facility included all of the 1879-era amenities that a student might want (i.e. wooden floors, kerosene lamps, etc.) Today, only shards of pottery and an occasional piece of the brick foundation are the only bits of evidence that remain from this early residence hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-jdarst-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;John Darst&quot; alt=&quot;John Darst&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;John Darst&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Darst died on Aug. 6, 1895. Darst moved his family to Walnut Grove/Eureka in 1851 and quickly became involved in the life of the village and the educational institution that had been founded here shortly before his arrival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darst became one of the greatest &amp;ldquo;boosters&amp;rdquo; of both the town of Eureka and of Eureka College for the remainder of his life. He served for 40 years on the Board of Trustees, and he chaired that body from 1873-1895. He was one of the strongest financial supporters of the institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Darst was a member of the Christian Church and he was an abolitionist. During the Civil War, five of his sons served in the Union Army.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/august-06</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/august-06</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>July 30</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On July 28, 1862, one of Eureka College’s founders, Elijah Dickinson, died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-edickinson-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Elijah Dickinson&quot; alt=&quot;Elijah Dickinson&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Elijah Dickinson&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Ben Major&amp;rsquo;s death in 1852, Elijah Dickinson took leadership of the Board of Trustees that administered the Walnut Grove Academy. It was under Dickinson&amp;rsquo;s leadership that efforts were conducted that resulted in the chartering of Eureka College in 1855.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elijah W. Dickinson, Class of 1860, was the first graduate of Eureka College and was a son of Elijah Dickinson. The senior Dickinson, a veteran of the War of 1812, led the special farewell services that were conducted at the old Meeting House when the boys of Company G of the 17th Illinois Infantry went off to join the Civil War. Two of his sons, Roger and Charles, were members of that group and Elijah W. would later serve in another company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On July 28, 1887, Emory Ross, Class of 1907, was born. Ross and his wife, Myrta Pearson Ross, Class of 1913, spent most of their lives serving as Christian missionaries in the Belgian Congo. Together, the couple wrote several books about their experiences in Africa and the path that African peoples were taking toward independence in the era of decolonization. During their work in Africa, Emory and Myrta Pearson Ross became acquainted with the work of Dr. Albert Schweitzer, and they hosted him on his first trip to the United States in 1949.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-dSandifer-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Durward Sandifer&quot; alt=&quot;Durward Sandifer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Durward Sandifer&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 26, 1900, Durward Vladimir Sandifer, Class of 1924, was born. Sandifer taught at Eureka College for a few years following his graduation, but he is best remembered for his service as a career diplomat in the U.S. State Department. In the years following WW II, Sandifer was the assistant to Eleanor Roosevelt who was serving as the U.S. delegate to the newly established United Nations. It was Sandifer who wrote the draft document of what eventually became the United Nations&#39; Universal Declaration of Human Rights. That document, after much debate and revision, was adopted unanimously by the member states of the United Nations on Dec. 10, 1948. Called by some a &amp;ldquo;mission statement for the world,&amp;rdquo; the Universal Declaration of Human Rights is among the most important documents of the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-30</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-30</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>July 23</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-amyers-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Abisha Myers&quot; alt=&quot;Abisha Myers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Abisha Myers&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 25, 1813, Abisha Myers was born. Abisha and his brother Elias were among the founders of Eureka College, and both served on the Board of Trustees for many years. In addition to being a large landowner in Woodford County, Abisha Myers was also an early businessman in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myers Tavern was the name of the first hotel and saloon to exist in Walnut Grove (later Eureka). The facility was located on the north end of town near the railroad tracks (where the laundromat is currently located). This business enterprise was related to the history of Eureka College in two rather interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, when construction of Recitation Hall was threatened in 1857 due to the nationwide economic depression called the Panic of 1857, John Darst, Elias Myers and Abisha Myers stepped forward to save the day. All three of these community leaders mortgaged their property to the last dime in order to guarantee that construction could continue on the three-story brick structure that for many years would &amp;ldquo;be&amp;rdquo; Eureka College. Yes, Abisha Myers mortgaged his beloved tavern for the greater good that would come to Eureka by having it become a college town. Abisha Myers - visionary, opportunist, wise businessman - likely a combination of all three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1861 the Myers Tavern played another important role in the history of Eureka College. It was at that site that the actual recruiting took place when Company G of the 17th Illinois Infantry formed. We do all speak fondly of the Recruiting Elm events that took place on campus in April 1861 after the shots were fired at Fort Sumter. A spontaneous patriotic event did take place on campus ‘neath that elm, but the real job of forming a company took place about two weeks later when volunteers met and signed up for service at the Myers Tavern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-aFisher-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Asa Starbuck Fisher&quot; alt=&quot;Asa Starbuck Fisher&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Asa Starbuck Fisher&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 25, 1849, Asa Starbuck Fisher and Susan Palmer were married. Fisher was the first professor at the Walnut Grove Seminary, and he had just completed his first year of teaching at that early institution when he married Ms. Palmer. The Fishers eventually had one child, Laura E. Fisher, Eureka College Class of 1868.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-23</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-23</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>July 16</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;July 12, 1923&lt;/strong&gt;, the smell of smoke filled the air at Eureka College. The Mission Tabernacle was destroyed by fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nathaniel S. Haynes wrote of this structure in his &amp;ldquo;History of the Disciples of Christ in Illinois 1819&amp;ndash;1914.&amp;rdquo;  He wrote, &amp;ldquo;In 1884 a commodious audience-room, designed by Professor Radford, was erected on the college campus, called &amp;lsquo;The Tabernacle.&amp;rsquo; It is 80 by 100 feet in dimensions, seating 1,200 people. Its cost was &lt;sup&gt;$&lt;/sup&gt;4,000, which was paid by citizens of the community. It stands on gently sloping ground that forms a natural amphitheater. For a period of 12 years the State Missionary Convention assembled there. It has served the college on commencement and other occasions, and the community for various purposes, including in the later years Chautauqua programs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/tabernacle-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;The Mission Tabernacle&quot; alt=&quot;The Mission Tabernacle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;The Mission Tabernacle&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For many years, this structure was the largest auditorium space in central Illinois and it was used by many groups for a wide variety of events. It was this facility, perhaps more than anything else that made Eureka, Ill., known throughout the region in the late-19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; and early-20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centuries. Famous visitors who spoke in The Mission Tabernacle included Booker T. Washington, William Jennings Bryan, Billy Sunday, Carry A. Nation, Adlai Stevenson Sr., Robert LaFollette and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the debris from the structure had been cleared, Professor Jacob Rinker envisioned the use of the space as an open-air amphitheater. The land would be developed for this purpose over the next decade. The western portion of the Cerf College Center is also situated upon the space where the Mission Tabernacle once stood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 13, 1930&lt;/strong&gt;, marked the final day of the last Chautauqua that was ever held at Eureka College. For more than 30 years the college had hosted these summertime festivals that attracted major speakers and great entertainment to the community of Eureka. The events drew visitors to the campus from all parts of central Illinois. At one time there were 800 families that were annual subscribers to the Chautauqua and held season tickets to the events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/chautauqua-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Partial view of Chautauqua tenting grounds&quot; alt=&quot;Partial view of Chautauqua tenting grounds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Partial view of Chautauqua tenting grounds&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By 1930, because of changing mores in American society and the greater freedom afforded by the automobile, there was waning interest in the old-fashioned camp-meeting summer revival nature of the Chautauqua events that were held at the college. Although the end of the series was not officially announced in 1930, there was no event the following year and the series is yet to be revived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;July 16, 1980&lt;/strong&gt;, the Republican Party, meeting at its convention in Detroit, Mich., nominated Ronald W. Reagan (Eureka College Class of 1932) as its candidate for the presidency of the United States. On the following evening, Reagan accepted the nomination.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-16</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-16</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>July 9</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;July 9, 1797&lt;/strong&gt;, noted British statesman Edmund Burke died. Later, when the young men attending Walnut Grove Academy decided to form a literary society that would encourage spirited debate and intellectual alacrity, they named their organization the Edmund Burke Society. Literary societies such as the Edmund Burke Society, the Malthusian Society and the Periclesian Society existed at the campus until the early part of the 20th century when such organizations were replaced by fraternities and sororities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Edmund Burke&amp;rsquo;s most often quoted maxims: &amp;ldquo;The only thing necessary for the triumph of evil is for good men to do nothing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/recitation-hall-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Recitation Hall&quot; alt=&quot;Recitation Hall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Recitation Hall&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;July 8, 1858&lt;/strong&gt;, The Washington Investigator carried a brief notice that described the construction of Recitation Hall at Eureka College. The construction of the three-story brick structure that is today known as Burrus Dickinson Hall [formerly the Administration Building] was a significant event in the early life of Eureka College. For many years, that single building was Eureka College. It housed nearly every office and classroom that was necessary for the institution&amp;rsquo;s operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-HOpritchard-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Harry Otis Pritchard&quot; alt=&quot;Harry Otis Pritchard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Harry Otis Pritchard&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;July 10, 1876&lt;/strong&gt;, Harry Otis Pritchard was born. He served as president of Eureka College from 1913&amp;ndash;1919, and as a human dynamo, his tenure was associated with an expansive building program that energized the campus at multiple levels. Pritchard Gymnasium [now Pritchard Fine Arts Center] and Vennum Science Hall [now Vennum-Binkley Hall] were constructed on the campus during the administration of President Pritchard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pritchard was a native of Johnson County, Indiana. He earned his A.B. at Butler College (1902), his A.M. at the University of Indianapolis (1903), and his B.D. from Yale University (1906).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to his appointment at Eureka College, Pritchard had served as pastor at Cotner College in Bethany, Nebraska, from 1907&amp;ndash;13 (his other responsibilities there included coaching football and the debate teams). He served as president at Eureka College for six years, and upon leaving that position, World Call noted his legacy in that &amp;ldquo;practically a new physical plant has been built, endowment largely increased, college attendance advanced 300 per cent, and academic standing lifted to the first rank among Illinois schools.&amp;rdquo; When he left Eureka in 1919, Pritchard took the position of General Secretary for the National Board of Education for the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), a position he held until the time of his death.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-9</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-9</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>July 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-mCHawk-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;Mary Gertrude Clark Hawk&quot; alt=&quot;Mary Gertrude Clark Hawk&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;Mary Gertrude Clark Hawk&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 29, 1882, Robert Mofett Allison Hawk died. Hawk became the first alumnus of Eureka College to be elected to the United States Congress. (Incidentally, his wife, Mary Gertrude Clark Hawk (Class of 1861) was the first woman to graduate from Eureka College.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On July 3, 1898, Eureka College alumnus Frank Frantz of Roanoke joined Theodore Roosevelt and the Rough Riders as they took San Juan Hill in Cuba during the Spanish-American War. In the years following the war, Frantz served as the last governor of the Oklahoma Territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;article class=&quot;small-12 large-4 columns clearfix&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/profile-wJBryan-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;William Jennings Bryan&quot; alt=&quot;William Jennings Bryan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;William Jennings Bryan&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/article&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 4, 1909, William Jennings Bryan, a three-time candidate for president of the United States, spoke at Eureka College. It was his second visit to the college; he had first spoken there in 1907.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/160/blog/img/wJBryan-web.jpg&quot; title=&quot;William Jennings Bryan visits with locals on the Eureka College campus&quot; alt=&quot;William Jennings Bryan visits with locals on the Eureka College campus&quot; /&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;William Jennings Bryan, seated under the flag, visits with the locals on the Eureka College campus in this photo from the early 1900s.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On July 4, 1929, there was tragedy on the Eureka College campus. During an evening fireworks display, a rocket misfired and exploded in a crowd that had gathered along College Avenue. A toddler, the son of Eureka College legendary coach Ralph McKinzie, Class of 1923, was killed by the explosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On June 30, 1954, Eureka College president Burrus Dickinson resigned. He had served since 1939. The next day, July 1, 1954, Ira Langston assumed the presidency. He would serve until 1977, the longest tenure of any Eureka College president.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog/articles/july-2</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
