<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Eureka College @ 160</title>
    <description>The &#39;This Week in Eureka College History&#39; column commemorates the 160th anniversary of the founding of Eureka College on Feb. 6, 1855. The column is scheduled to run weekly through Feb. 6, 2016.</description>
    <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 14:56:45 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 14:56:45 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>March 26</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Roger Burrus Dickinson died on March 28, 1911. Fifty years prior to his death, Dickinson had been enrolled as a student at Eureka College when the Civil War began. He was among the young men who gathered beneath the &amp;ldquo;Recruiting Elm&amp;rdquo; and he, along with his brother Charles, eventually joined Company G of the 17th Illinois Infantry. In an impassioned letter written two days after the Battle of Shiloh, Dickinson informed his family of Charlie&amp;rsquo;s injury. Dickinson wrote, &amp;ldquo;He needs better care than he can have here,&amp;rdquo; and encouraged assistance from home - &amp;ldquo;I want you to come &amp;hellip; several of the citizens ought to come.&amp;rdquo; Charles did survive. In subsequent years, Roger Dickinson returned to Eureka where he became a businessman and civic leader. In the late 1890s he established the Dickinson Canning Factory on the north end of town. It would later be sold to the Libby Corporation in the 1920s. Roger was the grandfather of Burrus Dickinson, who was a president of Eureka College and the namesake of Burrus Dickinson Hall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 27, 1993, groundbreaking ceremonies were held to mark the beginning of construction of the Donald B. Cerf College Center. The Cerf Center has had great impact not only upon the life of Eureka College but also the community of Eureka and beyond. The building was designed to house the Ronald Reagan Exhibit; a 400-seat auditorium; multipurpose breakout rooms that could be used for meetings or dining events; &amp;ldquo;The Burgoo&amp;rdquo; - a campus center; and much-needed office space for Student Programs and Services. The building was constructed in one year and opened to the public on March 21, 1994.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun Fact: On March 24, 1997, Frances McDormand was awarded the Oscar for Best Actress at the Academy Awards ceremony for her role in the film &amp;ldquo;Fargo.&amp;rdquo; McDormand won the Oscar for her memorable portrayal of Marge Gunderson, a pregnant police chief investigating three murders. How is this event related to Eureka College? Frances McDormand is the daughter of Vernon W. McDormand from the Eureka College Class of 1953.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-26</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-26</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>March 19</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 19, 1912, Eureka College launched a campaign to raise money to construct a gymnasium. The success of that drive would lead to the construction of Pritchard Gymnasium (now Pritchard Fine and Performing Arts Center), which was completed by 1915. The construction of a gymnasium was one of the first signs that marked the maturation, and the permanence, of Eureka College. The creation of the building, like the establishment of Melick Library in 1967, marked the establishment of a building dedicated to a specific purpose in the life of the college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 18, 1926, the E Tribe organization was established at Eureka College as an association for students who had lettered in sports. The group was created by legendary coach Ralph McKinzie, Class of 1923, and it represents one of the first ways that he left his mark on the athletic program at Eureka College. E Tribe still exists as an active organization in the life of the college. The group continues to recognize the accomplishments of Eureka College students as scholar-athletes. Members and alumni are involved in annual fundraising efforts to support the intercollegiate athletic program that has played such an integral part of the history and tradition of the institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 21, 1994, two historic events took place. First, it was the opening day for the Donald B. Cerf College Center. The official dedication for the new building would take place in May 1994, but as fourth term classes began in 1994 the new building became operational.
That evening, the Eureka College community gathered in the gymnasium in Reagan Center for a very special homecoming and pep rally event as the Eureka College men&amp;rsquo;s basketball team, the reigning 1994 NAIA Division II national champions, returned to the campus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-19</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-19</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>March 12</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The old campus bell tolled on March, 10, 1923, marking the death of Louis Oliver Lehman, Class of 1901. This beloved young president of Eureka College had died of typhoid fever at age 45. Lehman came from Sterling, and as a student was a member of the first basketball team organized at the college. After graduation, he was a pastor at area churches and then was named president of the college in 1919, just as the Division of Higher Education of the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ) was starting a massive campaign - the “Men and Millions Campaign” - to build endowment at the several colleges and universities that were related to the denomination. Each institution was given a quota of funding that was deemed necessary to keep the school viable and sustainable. It was generally understood that those schools that could not meet the funding levels might not remain in operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Lehman was told that he had to raise $400,000 by 1923 in order to meet the quota. This was a tremendous amount of money, especially in 1920 dollars, and the prospect of raising such an amount during a period of burgeoning economic depression in America&amp;rsquo;s farming heartland was especially daunting. Lehman traveled for three years meeting with prospective donors and presenting the case for why supporters should help build the endowment of Eureka College. Lehman also made the bold decision to seek support from the Rockefeller Foundation - a move that many believed was unrealistic. In the end, the decision was a brilliant one as the Rockefeller Foundation pledged $135,000 to support Eureka College&amp;rsquo;s endowment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The efforts took a toll on the president’s health, however. Six weeks after his death, Eureka College announced that it had exceeded its &amp;ldquo;Men and Millions&amp;rdquo; quota by more than $45,000. Louis Oliver Lehman was recognized as a martyr to the institution who gave his all that Eureka College might survive and prosper. The Board of Trustees said of Lehman, &amp;ldquo;His unbounded faith, his high ideals and his quiet determination were the source of constant inspiration and encouragement to us seeking to establish the college on a more stable basis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-12</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-12</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>March 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;David Deweese was born on March 7, 1801, in Knox County, Ky. One of the founders of Eureka College, Deweese is honored by having a residence hall in the Founders’ Court complex named in his memory. He served as a trustee of the college in its first year, 1855. Deweese was considered to be among the old-timers in the community of Walnut Grove/Eureka. His family had moved to the region in 1830, which was about five years prior to the large migration of Christian County, Ky., residents, so Deweese was already well-established in the settlement when the new emigrants arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 8, 1950, the first debate meet to be held on the Eureka College campus took place. The event was organized by Ivan Sparling, professor of speech and coach of the college&amp;rsquo;s debate team. Debate had long been an essential part of the institution&amp;rsquo;s heritage from the early days of the Walnut Grove Academy. In the early 1850s students organized the Pedotrophian (Boy Nurturing) Society in order to sponsor events that focused on extemporaneous public elocution. Sometimes the matters that were debated focused on integral public issues of the day, but at other times the debates centered on items that were nonsensical. One such forum was held on the topic &amp;ldquo;Resolved that the dishrag is more essential to housekeeping than the broom.&amp;rdquo; The records do not indicate which side prevailed in that particular contest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that early athletic &amp;ldquo;fight songs&amp;rdquo; associated with Eureka College include the institution&amp;rsquo;s success in debates and other co-curricular activities along with athletic victories. In &amp;ldquo;A Eureka Glee,&amp;rdquo; composed by Clyde L Lyon (Class of 1905), we find the verse:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In athletics, oratory, music and debate,
We always win our share of firsts, we stand in well with fate:
And so we fling our banner high, the old gold and maroon;
Our eyes delight to see it wave, it sets our voices in tune.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/march-2</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>February 26</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On Feb. 27, 1856, the Trustees of Eureka College made the first purchase of land to enlarge the landholding of Eureka College. The original campus consisted of 15 acres that had been donated to the institution by Elias B. Myers and James Conover. The new addition, which was an additional 12 acres, was purchased from Abisha M. Myers for $150.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 4, 1866, co-founder of the Christian Church movement Alexander Campbell died at his home in Bethany, W.V. Campbell was buried on a mountainside facing his home and the institution, Bethany College, that he had established. In 1900, and again in 2000, students from Eureka College traveled to the grave site of Campbell to obtain ivy from that site and transplant it on the Eureka College campus. During his lifetime, Campbell made two trips to Walnut Grove (Eureka). The first was in 1847 (before the Walnut Grove Seminary was founded) and the second was in 1853 (while the Walnut Grove Academy was in operation). It was during Campbell’s 1847 visit that the decision to build the first Christian Church in Walnut Grove was made. PHOTO: A plaque on Burgess Memorial Hall commemorates the 1900 trip by Eureka College students to obtain ivy from Alexander Campbell’s grave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 4, 1952, Ronald W. Reagan (Class of 1932) and Nancy Davis were married. PHOTO: Ronald Reagan, left, and his wife, Nancy, attended the 1957 commencement ceremony at Eureka College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Construction of Melick Library began on March 1, 1966.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 05:29:54 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/feb-26</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/feb-26</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>February 12</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;John T. Jones was born Feb. 10, 1795. One of the early settlers to move to Walnut Grove, which later became Eureka, Jones established the first school in the community. Jones’ school for girls predated the establishment of the Walnut Grove Seminary in 1848. The school that Jones established was only open for one semester in the fall of 1847. Fifteen girls were enrolled there, and Emily Jones, the wife of John, and her daughter Susan served as the teachers. After a measles epidemic swept the community in December 1847 the school disbanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Harvey Rowell. Class of 1861, was born on Feb. 10, 1833. Rowell was among Eureka College students who enlisted in Company G of the 17th Illinois Infantry during the Civil War. When Captain Otis Asa Burgess resigned from his post, it was Rowell who was selected to serve as the new captain of the company. After the Civil War, Rowell returned to central Illinois and became a lawyer. He was elected to the U.S. Congress and served from 1883 to 1891, representing the Bloomington-Normal area.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;On Feb. 13, 1855, the Illinois state legislature granted a charter establishing Abingdon College. This institution, located in Abingdon, Ill., was another institution like Eureka College that was formed in association with the Christian Church movement. In 1885 Abingdon College would close its doors forever when it merged with Eureka College.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;The Rev. Raymond F. McCallister Sr., Class of 1931, died on Feb. 8, 1993. Rev. McCallister served in various pastoral and administrative roles within the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ). During the 1950s, Rev. McCallister hosted “The Protestant Hour,” one of the first syndicated religious programs on U.S. television. In 1983, Eureka College dedicated the newly remodeled upstairs room of the Chapel building as Raymond F. McCallister Hall. Each year the college awards the Raymond F. McCallister Fellowship to an entering student who is considering becoming an ordained minister in the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ).&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/feb-12</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/feb-12</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>February 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Tressler died on Feb. 2, 1853. This young German emigrant had settled in the community of Walnut Grove sometime in the 1840s. Like his father before him, he had learned the craft of carpentry, and it was by this trade that he made a living in his newly adopted home. In 1847 Jonathan Tressler constructed the very first Christian Church in Walnut Grove (at the current site of the Civil War monument in Olio Cemetery), and the following year he constructed the Walnut Grove Seminary - the very first manifestation of what grew to become Eureka College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At his death, he left his estate to the Walnut Grove Academy. This donation was the first bequest received by the institution, and it marked the start of the endowment fund.
On Feb. 5, 1900, the Eureka College Board of Trustees accepted the resignation of President J.N. Hardin whose administration as president had begun in 1896. His tenure was characterized by declining enrollment and financial hardship. In more than a mere chronological sense, his was the last administration of the 19th century. Several of his successors - most notably Presidents Hieronymus, Pritchard and Lehman - would provide a sense of new life and renewed vision for the institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Royal Humbert was born on Feb. 3, 1910. Named after the legendary Christian missionary Royal Dye, it seems natural that Royal Humbert would eventually become a noted theologian and professor of religion and philosophy at Eureka College. He joined the faculty in 1948 and taught until his retirement in the mid-1970s. His wife, Lois, joined the faculty in 1954 as professor of piano and organ and director of the hand bell choir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Humbert was known for being a rigorous teacher and a productive scholar. During his tenure at Eureka College he produced “A Compend of Alexander Campbell&amp;rsquo;s Theology with Commentary in the Form of Critical and Historical Footnotes” edited by Royal Humbert (St. Louis: Bethany Press, 1961).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/feb-2</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.eureka.edu/160/blog//articles/feb-2</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
